<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: personal | (cons 'hack *life*)]]></title>
  <link href="http://kisom.github.com/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kisom.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-02-11T19:58:56+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://kisom.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kyle Isom]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[coder@kyleisom.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[my docs got dropped]]></title>
    <link href="http://kisom.github.com/blog/2011/12/31/my-docs-got-dropped/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-31T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://kisom.github.com/blog/2011/12/31/my-docs-got-dropped</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My docs are in the stratfor leak.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I'm not too worried though; everything in there is either out of date
(i.e. that credit card already expired and I have a new one now), my
password was used only on that site (but was a 22 character phrase with
punctuation), and that email address was only used for stratfor. My
address was also already published due to my domain names (most of which
are now privately registered, but I couldn't always afford that).</p>

<p>Now that I have a doc drop that actually affects me (the mtgox break-in
gathered a similarly difficult and unique password, and besides some spamming
from idiots trying to exploit the situation with new bitcoin services
there was no fallout), I can talk about what I think of the spate of
LulzSec-style attacks this year. And that is - getting mad at Anonymous,
LulzSec, AntiSec, or whatever the nom du jour is, is an exercise in futility
and ignorance. It's like getting mad at your five year old for getting into
the cookie jar you left on the kitchen table. Your antiquated and
ineffective security mechanism (the kid couldn't <em>possibly</em> get on the
table) should have been replaced by something more effective (maybe locking
it in the pantry, overkill for a cookie jar though).</p>

<p>The issue is it's 2011 (almost 2012) and we've been doing this for a while
now. The rampant incompetence of people setting up these sites should be
made a crime. That would be a far better use of legislative effort than the
brain dead attempts at anti-piracy we're seeing now. The script kiddies
aren't exhibiting any serious talent, the security (I use the term loosely
here) people are setting up is juvenile.</p>

<p><strong> Afterthoughts: </strong></p>

<p>As <a href="http://hackerne.ws/user?id=gyardley">gyardley</a> pointed out on
<a href="http://hackerne.ws/item?id=3411236">hackerne.ws</a>, when I compare the
LulzSec-type script kiddies to five-year-olds, I don't mean to create
the impression that they shouldn't be held legally liable. I do fear,
however, that focusing on legal actions against those responsible will
cause us to lose focus on the bigger problem.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
