<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: OS X | (cons 'hack *life*)]]></title>
  <link href="http://kisom.github.com/blog/categories/os-x/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kisom.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-02-22T10:51:59+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://kisom.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kyle Isom]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[coder@kyleisom.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on Mountain Lion]]></title>
    <link href="http://kisom.github.com/blog/2012/02/17/thoughts-on-mountain-lion/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-17T20:16:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://kisom.github.com/blog/2012/02/17/thoughts-on-mountain-lion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the great things about paradigm shifts is we can throw out the old
and start from scratch, getting rid of all the old cruft that's built up over
time. Computers are no different, and the tablet revolution has allowed us
to rethink a few things. It looks like Apple is finally converging some of the
lessons learned with iOS and OS X. So, let's take a look at some of these
ideas:</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The App Store as a sole source of software</h3>

<p>I've heard a lot of complaints about this. The fact of the matter is that for
the average user, this makes sense. It limits the exposure due to malware. For
users who need expanded privileges, it is <em>extremely</em> easy to do. This follows
a principle of secure by default and requiring a decision on the user's part
to open up their system. Does Apple benefit? Surely. However, in this case the
decision also benefits users.</p>

<h3>Messages</h3>

<p>We are surrounded by a variety of chat systems. On mobile phones, SMS reigns
supreme; while on the desktop, there are more chat protocols than you can
shake a stick at. Bringing Messages onto the desktop starts to unify the
two systems. While Jabber and AIM / OSCAR are two very common protocols, it
would be good to see Twitter and perhaps even IRC. (While I would love to
see SILC supported, I don't expect to see that anytime soon). One other thing
missing is OTR support. While the iMessage compatibility is interesting, lack
of Twitter and OTR support make it not compelling enough for me to switch over
as my chat client<a href="#footnotes">*</a>.</p>

<h3>XCode</h3>

<p>Apple is now providing a much smaller download with just the compiler and
commandline tools needed to use <a href="http://mxcl.github.com/homebrew/">Homebrew</a>
or other package management systems.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>We're starting to see some of the benefits of tablet revolution folded back
into the desktop and laptop realm. For normal users, these changes create a
more streamlined experience and improve the overall security of the system.
For developers, there are some changes to simplify non-iOS / Cocoa developers'
setups. I think this is a step in the right direction.</p>

<p>Except that it's called "Mountain Lion."</p>

<h3><a name="footnotes">Footnotes</a></h3>

<ol>
<li>I currently use <a href="http://www.adium.im/">Adium</a> for my chat and twitter client.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
